JUAN CARLOS URCIA BAREA

331 16th Street, Apartment 3 · Brooklyn, NY 11215 jcurciabarea@gmail.com · www.jcurciabarea.info · +1 301-525-1319

Summary: Motivated analyst with a passion for political economy, macroeconomics, finance, and labor. My current work at Moody's focuses on the credit risk of governments in Latin America. Previously I served as a policy advisor to U.S. Senator Ben Cardin on labor and the social safety net, among other issue areas. My skill set centers on policy and economic analysis, writing, and advising.

EDUCATION

Princeton University Princeton, NJ

Master in Public Affairs | School of Public and International Affairs August 2020 to May 2022

Brown University Providence, RI Bachelor of Arts | History August 2013 to May 2017

EMPLOYMENT

Moody's Investors Service

New York, NY

July 2022 to Present

Associate Analyst | Sovereign Risk Group

- Portfolio of sovereign credits: Argentina, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Honduras, Panama; Kenya; Bahamas; and MDBs: Inter-American Development Bank (IDB), IDB Invest, Fondo Latinoamericano de Reservas (FLAR).
- Conduct research and analysis of credit risk for portfolio issuers, focusing on economic, political, fiscal, and event risk factors by assisting lead analysts in credit rating monitoring and evaluation for rating committees.
- Assist in writing as well as data analysis and visualization for regular publications and research pieces.
- Collect, maintain, and analyze data on key economic and fiscal indicators through Excel and Haver Analytics.
- Interface and maintain relationships with government officials, investors, and clients, and have represented Moody's on calls, meetings, and as part of delegation visits to issuer countries and IMF annual meetings.

U.S. Department of Commerce

Princeton, NJ

Graduate Consultant | Office of the U.S. Secretary of Commerce

August 2021 to January 2022

- Graduate capstone project to advise the Office of the Secretary on implementation of the CHIPS Act.
- Developed recommendations for the creation of the National Semiconductor Technology Center (NSTC) by researching and analyzing industry trends, interviewing leading firms, academics, and defense analysts.
- Independently created and designed the team's capstone report in Adobe InDesign.

U.S. Department of the Treasury

Washington, DC

Graduate Intern | Office of International Financial Markets

May to August 2021

- Created a heatmap dashboard in Excel tracking macroeconomic and financial risk indicators across various advanced economies and emerging markets, pulling data from Haver Analytics.
- Drafted internal memos reviewing trends such as sovereign-bank debt nexus, housing market activity, credit and asset prices as indicators of bubbles, and sovereign dollar debt crises.

U.S. Senator Benjamin L. Cardin

Legislative Correspondent

Washington, DC

July 2018 to July 2020

Staff Assistant

September 2017 to June 2018

- Assisted in writing and managing legislation, including the Government Employee Fair Treatment Act (P.L.116-1), which became law guaranteeing back-pay for furloughed workers during government shutdowns.
- Led office research and recommendations on the 2018-2019 35-day federal government shutdown and COVID-19 unemployment insurance and state fiscal relief legislative efforts as part of the CARES Act.
- Researched and wrote recommendation memos for bills, resolutions, nominations, Dear Colleague letters, constituent issues, breaking developments, and other action items for the Senator.
- Prepared and staffed the Senator for hearings and other developments before the U.S. Senate Committee on Finance and the U.S. Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works.
- Advised press team on policy issues and helped draft and edit press releases and statements.
- Wrote speeches, floor statements, and constituent responses on legislative efforts and political issues.
- Represented the Senator in meetings with stakeholders and political nominees.

U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Relations

Intern | Ranking Member, Democratic Staff

July to August 2016

Washington, DC

- Researched and circulated press clips on Southeast Asia security and foreign aid issues.
- Helped prepare staff and members for committee hearings, meetings, and external events.

U.S. Representative David N. Cicilline

Pawtucket, RI

Intern | Pawtucket District Office

May to July 2016

- Managed busy front office, supervised 10 events in the district, and logged constituent correspondence.
- Created an Excel database for major government and elected officials in Rhode Island for internal office use.

The Walt Disney Company

Burbank, CA

Intern | Corporate Strategy and Business Development

June to August 2015

- Conducted a financial analysis of a merger between two telecommunications firms.
- Collaborated on group research and slide deck on the "smart" ad tech industry landscape.

VOLUNTEERING AND COMMUNITY ACTIVITIES

Instituto Cervantes | Member and Student (2023-Present)

• Study the Spanish language and participate in Spanish and Latin American cultural events and activities.

Volunteer Income Tax Assistance (VITA) | SPIA Chapter Co-Lead and Volunteer (2021-2022)

Provided weekly tax filing services to low-income and disadvantaged residents of Mercer County, New Jersey.

SPIA First Generation and Low-Income (FLI) Students | Co-Lead and Co-Founder (2020-2022)

• Hosted FLI alumni for career talks and collaborate with university on programming for FLI students.

The Julis-Rabinowitz Center for Public Policy and Finance | Graduate Associate (2020-2022)

• Engaged in seminars on financial policy and economic history led by faculty and visiting experts.

Congressional Hispanic Staff Association (CHSA) | Alumnus (2016-2020)

• Participated in career development, networking, and volunteering activities.

LANGUAGES AND NATIONALITIES

- English: Native/Fluent | Spanish: Advanced | Japanese: Novice
- United States of America (citizen) | Spain (citizen)

RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Economics and Finance Statistics Microeconomics - Professor Amy Craft Quantitative Analysis – Professor David Lee Macroeconomics - Professor Gregor Jarosch Econometrics I – Professor Jordan Matsudaira Econometrics II – Professor Alexandre Mas Public Economics - Professor Henrik Kleven International Economics – Professor Silvia Weverbrock Program & Policy Evaluation - Professor Jean Grossman Financial Management - Professor Adam Shrager Growth, Finance, Crises - Professor Ashoka Mody **Politics** Macroeconomic Ideas - Professor Ashoka Mody Politics of Public Policy - Professor Andrew Moravcsik Domestic Politics - Professor Frances Lee Central Banking - Professor Alan Blinder Global Supply Chains - Professor Doyle Hodges The State - Professor Philip Pettit

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Professional: politics, economics, financial analysis, fiscal and debt metrics, statistical analysis, data visualization, graphic design, writing, editing, public speaking, event planning, customer service

Software: Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook); Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, InDesign); Econometric Analysis (Stata, R); Financial Research (Bloomberg Terminal, Haver Analytics, FactSet, Reuters); Programming (Python, Java, HTML/CSS); Communications (Slack, Signal, Zoom, Webex, Teams)

Policy: macroeconomics, fiscal and monetary policy, financial markets, banking, international affairs, globalization, poverty alleviation and social safety net, labor and unions, wealth and income inequality

Interests: photography, drawing, sudoku, computers, political and economic history, hiking, tennis, soccer